[SPEAKER_00]: The sutta today, it's Anguttara 321, it's called Purity, and it's a short sutta, but quite interesting, useful as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it starts by the Buddha addressing the bhikkhus saying, bhikkhus, there are these three kinds of purity.
[SPEAKER_00]: What three?
[SPEAKER_00]: Purity of body, purity of speech and purity of thought.
[SPEAKER_00]: What is purity of body?
[SPEAKER_00]: It is when a bhikkhu abstains from killing living creatures, stealing and in celibacy.
[SPEAKER_00]: That is called purity of body.
[SPEAKER_00]: What is purity of speech?
[SPEAKER_00]: It is when a bhikkhu abstains from false, malicious, harsh and trivial speech.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is called purity of speech.
[SPEAKER_00]: And what is purity of thought?
[SPEAKER_00]: It is when a bhikkhu, when there is a sensual desire internally, understands, there is a sensual desire internally for me.
[SPEAKER_00]: When there is no sensual desire internally, he understands, there is no sensual desire internally for me.
[SPEAKER_00]: He understands how unarisen sensual desire arises, and how arisen sensual desire is abandoned, and how abandoned sensual desire does not arise again in the future.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, when there is ill-will internally, he understands there is ill-will internally, for me.
[SPEAKER_00]: When there is no ill-will internally, he understands there is no ill-will internally for me.
[SPEAKER_00]: He understands how un-arisen ill-will arises, and how arisen ill-will is abandoned, and how abandoned ill-will does not arise again.
[SPEAKER_00]: When there is indolence and lethargy internally, he understands there is indolence and lethargy internally for me.
[SPEAKER_00]: When there is no indolence and lethargy internally, he understands there is no indolence and lethargy internally for me.
[SPEAKER_00]: He understands how un-arisen indolence and lethargy arises, and how arisen one is abandoned, and how abandoned one does not arise in the future.
[SPEAKER_00]: The fourth hindrance, eh... when there is restlessness and anxiety internally, he understands there is restlessness and anxiety internally for me.
[SPEAKER_00]: When there is no restlessness and anxiety, he understands that there is no restlessness and anxiety and he understands how un-arisen arises and how arisen is abandoned and how abandoned does not arising in the future.
[SPEAKER_00]: I forgot to do this part.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, when there is doubt internally, he understands there is doubt internally for me.
[SPEAKER_00]: When there is no doubt internally, he understands there is no doubt internally for me.
[SPEAKER_00]: He understands how un-arisen doubt arises and how arisen doubt is abandoned.
[SPEAKER_00]: And how abandoned doubt does not arise again in the future.
[SPEAKER_00]: That is called purity of thought.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then the Buddha finished with the verses saying these are these... there are these three kinds of purity.
[SPEAKER_00]: Purity of body, purity of speech and purity of thought.
[SPEAKER_00]: One who is clean and down with purity has washed off all evil they say.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, yes, as we can see, obviously, the sutta addresses the three fields of action.
[SPEAKER_00]: Action by body, by speech and thought.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, purity of body, self-explanatory, the precepts, the virtue, that's obviously
[SPEAKER_00]: Summed up in the in the three major ones, which is killing, stealing and insulipacy.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, it includes the domain of speech, which is anything from false speech, malicious, harsh, pointless, trivial, useless.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's avoiding those things.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's how one purifies the speech.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, the puritive thought in this sutta was
[SPEAKER_00]: expressed through, basically, understanding, full understanding, of the five hindrances.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, understanding of central desire, understanding the mind affected with central desire, when the mind is affected with central desire, understanding the mind unaffected by central desire, when the mind is not affected by it, understanding how it arises, understanding how it's abandoned, and understanding how it doesn't arise.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, and then the same goes for real will, indolence and lethargy, restlessness and anxiety, and then doubt as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: So,
[SPEAKER_00]: The interesting thing, and I think Venerable Nigam mentioned that on our Sutta website, is to note that how the Sutta does not define purity by the absence of the five hindrances.
[SPEAKER_00]: It defines it by knowing that they are present when they are present, and knowing that they are absent when they are absent.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that is the purity of thought.
[SPEAKER_00]: Purity of thought is not not having the mind affected with sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: The purity of thought is basically knowing the mind affected with sensuality as mind affected with sensuality, mind affected with doubt or ill-will as mind affected with those things.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's like...
[SPEAKER_00]: The point is obviously that presence of those things, the hindrances, presence of sensuality, ill-will, sloth and torpor, restlessness and anxiety and doubt,
[SPEAKER_00]: They're not in and of themselves.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're not hindrances.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's... when they're present in the mind, when that is not known, that is how one is hindered.
[SPEAKER_00]: When it's known, one is unhindered, pretty much, by the same thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: There was that other sutta, I think we might have done it even during these sessions, where it states exactly the same.
[SPEAKER_00]: It says there are things, they're like signs of beauty that come and mind picks up on them.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's like that in and of itself does not constitute a hindrance.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's when the mind, or rather when you attend wrongly to that experience of mind affected or mind seeing a sign of beauty, attending wrongly, ayoniso manasikāra, is how?
[SPEAKER_00]: You become hindered by it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's how that sensuality becomes something you're affected.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, say, there is a sign of ugly, sign of kind of aversion, which in and of itself, again, does not constitute a hindrance.
[SPEAKER_00]: Attending to it wrongly, you are hindered.
[SPEAKER_00]: In other words, not seeing the mind, not seeing the wild animal,
[SPEAKER_00]: To the sufficient extent, as something that's percipient or something that's, say, under the pressure of sign of beauty or sign of aversion, that's how you become hindered.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then he went to explain the same for these other five hindrances, saying, pretty much, like, being lazy, acting lazily after the meal and so on, is how you become hindered by indolence and lethargy, wrongly attending to that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Restlessness and anxiety.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, was it the doubt?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, the doubt says there are things that are... that lend themselves to doubt.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, again, still does not... do not constitute a hindrance of doubt.
[SPEAKER_00]: Only wrongly attending to the mind that's under the pressure of things that are ambiguous in the nature, is how you fall into the hindrance of doubt.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, learning how to attend rightly does not remove the whole picture, does not prevent the sign of beauty, or sign of ugly, or thing suitable to doubt, or lack of energy.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it prevents you falling into the framework of that hindrance, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: It prevents you being trapped by it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's what Nigga pointed out.
[SPEAKER_00]: There are hindrances when there is craving.
[SPEAKER_00]: And without ignorance, craving cannot exist, which means, basically, if you are rightly attending, or seeing the mind clearly to the right extent, as something that's under the pressure of, say, sign of beauty, you won't be affected amidst those things.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you are unhindered amidst the world of hindrances, pretty much.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, and that's... he gave a... he gave an analogy in his notes, saying, it's like a... if someone has the key,
[SPEAKER_00]: For a cell door, and knows for a fact, they can get out at will, whenever they want.
[SPEAKER_00]: Can you really call that an imprisonment?
[SPEAKER_00]: If nobody else knows about a key, only you, only you have it, even people that think you are trapped in, don't know about it, and you could, at will, just open the door and leave, would it be correct to say you are the one who is imprisoned?
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's the point.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, yeah, so the sutta is short, but I did kind of extrapolate a few practical questions.
[SPEAKER_00]: on the basis of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: As in, obviously, you know, we speak about purity of body, purity of virtue often, so we're not going to dwell on that too much.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can listen to the previous talks for that.
[SPEAKER_00]: But purity of speech and then, obviously, purity of thought is the most refined and it's not just about
[SPEAKER_00]: Say, avoiding thinking about certain things and so on, but it's measured by the clarity of the understanding of the animal, of the citta.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, to what extent... Say, when the sensuality arises, or ill-will, to what extent do you regard that experience as a whole, as mind affected with ill-will that I'm experiencing, or
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm affected by... affected by ill-will through basically experiencing this or that that upset me in the world and mind is not even seen in that equation.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, how much of it do you see like it's between you and the mind or how much of it do you see out between me and whatever circumstance in the world made me upset or made me lustful or made me doubtful?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because that's the point.
[SPEAKER_00]: You begin by not seeing the mind at all.
[SPEAKER_00]: So it's it's it's it's all there in the world.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's all on the level of sense objects and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: Through containers, through containers of virtue, purifying your speech, right choices and everything else we often talk about, you are, as I said many times before, creating some... a degree of some space in between where you could actually start to notice your mind as a thing in between there.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you might initially, like, oh, this upset me, or that made me full of desire.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, before that, or rather between you and what you're seeing, there is that animal sitting there, affected by that thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's what needs to be seen.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, fundamentally, that's really the root of the problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why you practice restraint.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why you pay attention to the choice of your actions.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because all of that feeds that animal that's initially invisible to you, that mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: So the purity of thought is measured and trained through noticing that state of the animal, not trying to get rid of it, not trying to change it, just containing it.
[SPEAKER_00]: When I say do things on the right level, it really just means contain them to the right extent.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if you're too preoccupied of trying to resolve something instantaneously, well, you don't want to be containing it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're afraid that it might spill out and so on, which means, okay, you haven't developed the container sufficiently enough.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why it's just... it's not even like... there is
[SPEAKER_00]: There's no other way, really.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, you can't bypass this.
[SPEAKER_00]: The only way to understand the mind to the full extent as something affected by a hindrance, and therefore you become unaffected by it, is to contain it to the extent necessary, to endure it to the extent necessary until that container is developed sufficiently enough.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is no other way.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, how much of that endurance and container
[SPEAKER_00]: Whether it's going to be unpleasant, or not so unpleasant, depends on how much you're really resisting the idea of it, or not.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, eh... Let me go back to this one.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then, the questions for reflection, that I, as I said, extrapolated.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, for example, and again, these things can be, you know, where if you say, okay, I don't see my mind, therefore this sutta doesn't apply to me.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, fundamentally, sure, you need to see your mind for this to make any sense, but that doesn't mean you shouldn't be trying, as I said there before.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, meditation, samādhi, any form of, say, composure, should be revolving
[SPEAKER_00]: And be preoccupied, really, with learning how to contain that mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: How to not, through ayoniso manasikāra, you yourself, spill out and blame the world, blame the circumstances, blame the sign of beauty, blame the sign of ugly, blame things suitable that lend themselves to doubt easily, as that which is doubt, as that which is ill-will.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's what samādhi is.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not about removing the whole picture and not experiencing any of those disturbing things.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's about training in their containment.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, any form of meditation should really be a informed reflection, to call it that way.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you can ask yourself, like, in regard to this sutta in particular, you could ask yourself, so, okay, how, like, my recent actions,
[SPEAKER_00]: Today, two days ago, I don't know, last week, as far as I can recently remember, how often were they driven by desire?
[SPEAKER_00]: Carelessness and ill-will.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that already implies how often did I look past the state of mind and acted towards the world for pleasure, avoiding pain, resolving doubt,
[SPEAKER_00]: Which implicitly, obviously, assumes that that's where the problem was.
[SPEAKER_00]: And even if I theoretically learned that that's not where the problem was, how often did I give in to my still ingrained habit of still acting out towards the domain of the world through body, speech and mind, even if... even despite theoretically knowing that that's not where I should be looking for solution.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, how often did I allow myself to act out?
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, obviously, if you thought, okay, I could have done better, maybe I did good, maybe I didn't.
[SPEAKER_00]: The point is, okay, it's not going to be perfect, but the point is to start to recognize, okay, how many times I didn't.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, how many times I actually didn't act out despite the pressure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because that's what this... why this sutta is important, because it tells you, see, that's already a level of purity.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, again, the initial view and attitude by most people would be complete absence of these hindrances is what purity is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Therefore, they'd fall into these self-hypnotic meditation techniques, not incidentally, because that's the layer when you are unaware of pretty much everything.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you feel like this is the purest because there is nothing there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, there's a lot there, obviously, it's just that you're not noticing it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the point is, the purity is not measured by the absence.
[SPEAKER_00]: The purity is measured by your clarity in regard to whatever's present of those disturbing, five disturbing things.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you ask yourself, how often did I act out?
[SPEAKER_00]: This many times, that, in this instance, that instance... How often I didn't?
[SPEAKER_00]: How often did I restrain myself?
[SPEAKER_00]: And the point is, as I said, to rewrite that expectation that the absence of those things all together is the benchmark.
[SPEAKER_00]: It isn't.
[SPEAKER_00]: But to start to develop the clarity in regard to the difference as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: The difference between, well, how was it when I acted out?
[SPEAKER_00]: When I gave in to my old assumptions?
[SPEAKER_00]: And how did it feel when I didn't?
[SPEAKER_00]: What's the difference between the two?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what's the difference between an enduring pressure to act out and then act out and enduring pressure to act out and not acting out?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because the reason people choose acting out perpetually, repeatedly, is because not acting out, at the time, feels like, oh, unbearable.
[SPEAKER_00]: I have to act out.
[SPEAKER_00]: I just have to act out.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'll deal with it later.
[SPEAKER_00]: I have to act out.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the more familiar you become with it, even in, like, through this kind of retroactive contemplation of, hmm, how did it feel when I actually restrained myself,
[SPEAKER_00]: How do you feel when I didn't?
[SPEAKER_00]: What was the difference?
[SPEAKER_00]: Even that can be gradually familiarizing you with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you actually get to understand and kind of develop a broader view that, well, it wasn't that bad.
[SPEAKER_00]: It feels that bad at the moment.
[SPEAKER_00]: But from a point of view of a bigger picture, I actually contained it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it wasn't too bad.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, next time, you can remind... well, you would be automatically reminded of that, if you frequently recollect those things.
[SPEAKER_00]: Next time, when it feels like, oh, I can't bear this, I have to act out.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's like, but I already...
[SPEAKER_00]: I bought it in the past.
[SPEAKER_00]: It wasn't...
[SPEAKER_00]: It was an end of the world, for sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, why don't I do it again?
[SPEAKER_00]: And it kind of re-inform your own context at the time when that pressure is really, like, trying to make you act.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, frequently recollecting that, reminding yourself, and, as I said, trying to discern the difference, even if it's like a vague, oh, it felt like this, felt like that, you don't need to be, like, like, you know, super psychologically accurate or something.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's more like just being familiar with the other side of things, such as pressure came up and I didn't act.
[SPEAKER_00]: First, you learn to not, again, not overshoot the mark, which is, pressure came up, I didn't act, but I feel like I must still get rid of the pressure, because that's what the purity is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, it's not.
[SPEAKER_00]: You learn that it isn't.
[SPEAKER_00]: The purity is simply maintaining the clear picture, regardless of what state of the wild animal is.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the animal can be kicking, screaming, trying to bite you.
[SPEAKER_00]: You realize, that's fine, as long as I don't give in to this and don't act out of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It will have to calm down, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what you understand.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's where that patient, the patient's khanti aspect comes from.
[SPEAKER_00]: So then, like, another, say, retroactive reflection that you can do, would be in regard to the speech.
[SPEAKER_00]: So it's the same principle, obviously, but now you're refining it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, you can say, yeah, I didn't act.
[SPEAKER_00]: I wanted really to do this.
[SPEAKER_00]: I tried to act out my body, but I didn't.
[SPEAKER_00]: However, you know, I did say something.
[SPEAKER_00]: It wasn't too bad, but it couldn't be better.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, now you are addressing that domain, the domain of speech.
[SPEAKER_00]: And again, you can do that as a daily practice, not out of some sort of neurosis, trying to find out the answers.
[SPEAKER_00]: They will then magically make the whole thing fall into place.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's more like, no, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm going through the motions of actively reminding myself
[SPEAKER_00]: of what I chose to do and what I didn't.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whether I chose restraint or giving in.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whether I spoke out of greed, out of aversion, out of irritation, out of hindrance, or I didn't.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not about learning something new, in that sense, like, as I said, digging up for new revelations, information.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's about just reminding the mind
[SPEAKER_00]: Of what it already knows, but it kind of tends to look past it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's not...
[SPEAKER_00]: These reflections, basically, if you're doing them for that purpose, it might take some time, as I said, to get used to it, but if you're doing it for that purpose, just this type of questioning, it's already forming a type of samādhi.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's already containing your mind rightly.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's already
[SPEAKER_00]: Increasing, however, you know, whatever, like, to whatever minuscule degree, it's already... but it's still increasing a some degree of clarity in regard to the whole picture.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, recollect, again, about your recent speech, about today, about yesterday, and you say, oh, I said something I shouldn't have.
[SPEAKER_00]: Again, you realize, okay, now it's not about resolving that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Making grand determinations.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'll never do this, and I'll never do that, and I'll never go there again, because like...
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like all of that secondary.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's about familiarizing yourself with the state of mind, with your current experience, that has recollected the fact that mind got the better of you, made you act.
[SPEAKER_00]: How does it feel now, when you shed light to that?
[SPEAKER_00]: It's gonna feel unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's the point.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sure, you might have a tendency, oh, I'm worthless and I'll have more... No, no, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now that's going too far.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, question that now.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it's about familiarization.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whether it's affecting the mind pleasantly, unpleasantly, that's not the point.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's the trap you should try and not fall into.
[SPEAKER_00]: Be concerned about how it feels.
[SPEAKER_00]: Either way, you're containing it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then,
[SPEAKER_00]: Extend the same reflection further, in the sense of like, eh...
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay, I did well or I didn't do well.
[SPEAKER_00]: Either way, this is how it feels.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is how the difference feels.
[SPEAKER_00]: Let me remind myself of the values I should try and then, eh... persist through, eh... tomorrow and next day and the day after.
[SPEAKER_00]: If the speech is beneficial, timely, necessary, if I'm unsure about it,
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, then I'll probably just veer on the side of restraint, but either way, remind yourself about choosing to speak, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: And when the pressure to say something builds up, again, you don't have to just every single time say no to it, but you need to have perspective in regard to it, regardless of how it feels.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that kind of brings me to the third point that you can be asking yourself and thinking about, which is...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, do you clearly or how clearly do you recognize the context behind any currently enduring pressure, any hindrance, while it is present?
[SPEAKER_00]: In other words, when you are acutely pressured to act out, towards sensuality or out of ill-will and so on,
[SPEAKER_00]: How much of the context do you still retain, or are able to retain?
[SPEAKER_00]: Is it like none?
[SPEAKER_00]: You only see it afterwards or you are able to keep some perspective?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, obviously, that's kind of something that should be, again, revisited, recollected, reminded and developed.
[SPEAKER_00]: And how do you develop that context?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, exactly how I just described the first two reflections.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's how you develop it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's how, through this frequent reminding,
[SPEAKER_00]: Of what's skillful, what's unskillful, the difference between acting out, the difference between not acting out and staying with the pressure.
[SPEAKER_00]: That is how you are, as I said, informing that context.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the clearer you become regarding that experience as a whole, then the acuteness of the hindrance will be diminished to that extent.
[SPEAKER_00]: In other words, hindrance can be, like, really almost overwhelming you, but the context remains to not act out,
[SPEAKER_00]: That it's the state of the mind that needs to be contained, not be projected onto the world, towards the sense objects, and then fall into a trap.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, through that gradual, as I said, broadening of that context, is how you eventually will stop acting out.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, like, obviously, you abandon course acting outs, but these, these, eh... finer ways, in terms of, like, the speech and so on, where even your intention might be ambiguous and stuff, well, that's how you get to uproot it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, you can't necessarily pinpoint as easily as these coarse forms of actions, and you don't have to, because if the context becomes imperturbable enough, that endurance is the way out, not acting out as the way out, anything within that will have to... will have to eventually completely be eradicated.
[SPEAKER_00]: So...
[SPEAKER_00]: So then, eh... Yeah, another thing you can be asking yourself,
[SPEAKER_00]: Following the same line of the five hindrances is, say, when you are not acutely pressured, do you recognize certain, say, environmental triggers, conditions, that would act as precursor to a hindrance, precursor to a pressure?
[SPEAKER_00]: As I said, obviously, they're going to be the obvious ones, which presumably you would have been avoiding well beforehand, but even the subtler ones.
[SPEAKER_00]: In other words, can you foresee
[SPEAKER_00]: Where certain experiences, signs and features of those experiences are leading to, before it's too late, before the pressure is too much and you can't stop now.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because that's obviously important.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's like... that's the value of like learning things beforehand, because if you don't start anticipating where a certain set of choices, actions and so on is taking you,
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, there will be no mind development for you, really.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's that simile of the cook that the Buddha talked about.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then the last one, which, yeah, it's kind of useful and ties in with what I already said, which is, can you recall an instance when a hindrance actually ceased on its own?
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, completely.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you didn't act out, you endured it, you contained it, and then, next thing you know, it's... it was gone.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, again, it's not because you're expecting to learn something new from it, but it's in order to recollect it, in order to bring it back, because there will be subtler aspects of that the mind is simply overlooking.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's to become more and more familiar with how did that feel.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, see, whenever there is an acute hindrance pressuring you to act out, towards desire, towards this, towards that, staying with the pressure feels like it has no end.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you can say no to your desire once or twice, but the pressure is still there, the pressure is still there, and basically the mind... well, you fall into this view,
[SPEAKER_00]: There and then, that, well, if you don't act out, this will be kind of trapping you and closing you this pressure forever.
[SPEAKER_00]: All that you know, like, and you can tell to yourself, no, of course, nothing lasts forever.
[SPEAKER_00]: I know it will stop.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_00]: The mind doesn't listen to that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you're telling to yourself, oh, everything will pass away and impermanence, but the mind doesn't understand that, doesn't hear it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why is that?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, as I said many times before, because it doesn't speak your language, the practical reason for the mind not really taking any heed of the fact that, yes, the pressure will have to cease, and you know it, yet the mind still acts like it will never cease, it's because, well, you haven't been reflecting on it long enough.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, you haven't been going through the repetition of those recollections sufficiently enough for it to sink in, for it, for the mind to really become convinced.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, yeah, yeah, of course, yeah, no, it will cease.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why you should be also, yeah, recollect the hindrance, recollect the triggers and so on, but also recollect the times when actually you didn't act out and the hindrance subsided on its own.
[SPEAKER_00]: The pressure was gone.
[SPEAKER_00]: You didn't act out, you didn't do anything on account of it and it was gone.
[SPEAKER_00]: How did that feel?
[SPEAKER_00]: Again, ask the question, don't necessarily seek the answer.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because asking the question
[SPEAKER_00]: Reveals the mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or leaves the mind with it, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the mind will remember how it felt.
[SPEAKER_00]: The animal will remember how it felt.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's really what you... whom you're asking for.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're not asking for yourself.
[SPEAKER_00]: How did it feel?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, it felt...
[SPEAKER_00]: It's irrelevant.
[SPEAKER_00]: How did it feel?
[SPEAKER_00]: And feel how it felt.
[SPEAKER_00]: Get the animal to feel it how it felt.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, next time, the acute pressure is there, trying to overwhelm you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Again, you might ask the question, but you might not even have to ask the question, because that is the exact instance that you've been recalling, recollecting, so the mind will now be reminded of what you reminded it beforehand, which is how it felt when the thing ceased, which means, oh, it will cease.
[SPEAKER_00]: And now the animal got it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sure, you can forget again.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why it's not like you do it once and you're done.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the point is to get the animal to feel the difference.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it knows the difference.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, even if somebody
[SPEAKER_00]: Made zero effort in practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: Simply by by going through experiences on a daily basis, there must have been an instance where there was an acute sensuality or ill will and for one reason or the other, a sutta or a puthujjana, knowing nothing of the dhamma, for whatever reason, was not able to act out.
[SPEAKER_00]: Was just left with that pent-up pressure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Couldn't act out, couldn't do anything about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it disappeared.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just that, you know, again, if if he's completely uninstructed, he will not know to recollect that, the difference, and start start highlighting the difference.
[SPEAKER_00]: He'll just look past it, and move on, and continue acting towards objects in the world as if they were the problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: But now you know better, so you want to recollect how it felt, to develop a context that will, regardless of how powerful the pressure might be,
[SPEAKER_00]: ceases... ceases immediately, like, eh... instantane... or, simultaneously, ce... eh... recognizes that it's end.
[SPEAKER_00]: It recognizes that doesn't matter how long this lasts, how acute it might get, I remember how it ends.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because every hindrance ends the same, through that feeling of it's gone, relieved, unhindered, no weight,
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that will be sufficient to remind the animal to not panic, not feel as enclosed and entrapped as it otherwise would.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why that's important.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why these reflections are the true meditations, really.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you're asking these questions, not for the sake of, as I said, intellectual reasoning or finding some, like, psychological answers, but
[SPEAKER_00]: Just to bring, shed the light and set up the context that are then left with the mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you can ask a question and then sit with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if the mind wanders away, come back, re-ask it or ask a different question in regards to similar.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the questioning part is what keeps you actively engaged, so you don't fall into the mindless mantra recitation or sensation watching method.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you're not asking for the sake of answers, really.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the questioning part is what engages you, but then you stop halfway through for the mind to feel, to discern answers, for the answers to sink down to the mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not for the sake of your theory.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's pretty much how you train in regard to purifying your thoughts.
[SPEAKER_00]: Broadening the context on the basis of not acting out of hindrances,
[SPEAKER_00]: Not trying to get rid of the pressure, containing it and finding the stable, untouched ground within that.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's pretty much it.